Elizabeth Wilson Collection Relating to Rhys Caparn
Elizabeth Wilson Collection Relating to Rhys Caparn
1933-2011
Wilson, Elizabeth
1 linear ft.
Artwork, correspondence, memorabilia, printed material, and wiritings relating to American abstract artist Rhys Caparn
4124026
Biographical History
Rhys Caparn (1909-1997) was an American sculptor and illustrator.
She was born on July 28, 1909 in Onteora Park, New York. Her father, Harold ap Rhys Caparn was the landscape architect for the Brooklyn Botanical Garden from 1912-1945.
Rhys studied at the Brearly School in New York City from 1918-1927, Bryn Mawr College from 1927-1929, Ecole Artistique des Animaux in Paris from 1929-1930, and Archipenko School of Art from 1931-1933. She is particularly remembered for her abstract animal sculptures and was a member of the American Abstract Artists and the Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors.
On September 9, 1935 she married Herbert Johannes Steele, an economic and business columnist who was known for making uncanny predictions about the stock market. She died in 1997 in Danbury, Connecticut.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Elizabeth Wilson Collection Relating to Rhys Caparn consists of artwork, correspondence, memorabilia, printed material, and wiritings relating to American abstract artist Rhys Caparn.
Artwork is divided into originals and reproductions.
Correspondence consists of personal incoming mail.
Memorabilia is divided into personal photos and miscellaneous.
Printed material is divided into clippings, exhibition catalogs, and exhibition invitations.
Writings contains biographical notes by another, biographical information by Rhys Caparn, and an essay.
Arrangement of the Collection
Artwork is in no particular order. Correspondence is arranged chronologically with undated material at the end. Memorabilia is in no particular order. Printed Material (including clippings, exhibition catalogs, and exhibition inivitations) are arranged chronologically with undated material at the end. Writings are arranged by page number when applicable.
Separated Material
Two copies of Rhys Caparn by Robert Beverly Hale, and one copy of American Abstract Artists 1936-1966 edited by The American Abstract Artists, with introduction by Ruth Gurin, have been transferred to Rare Books.
Other Related Finding Aids
See also the
Rhys Caparn Papers
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Sculptors; Caparn, Rhys, 1909-1997.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Illustrators -- United States.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Women artists -- United States.; Women sculptors -- United States.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Black-and-white negatives.; Color negatives.; Exhibition catalogs.; Artists.; Illustrators.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Michele Wilson, 2012.
Inventory
- Artwork
  - Originals (Box 1)
  - Reproductions, includes negatives; 3 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming, 1963-1988; undated (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Address lists (Oversize 1)
  - Certificate, Accademia Bedriacense, 1984 (Oversize 1)
  - Personal photos, includes negatives (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, membership cards, notes, price lists (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Clippings, 1942-2011; undated; a number of articles by or about Johannes Steele; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1956-1988; undated; a number of articles by or about Johannes Steele; 2 folders (Oversize 1)
  - Exhibition catalogs, 1933-1978; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Exhibition invitations, 1957-1984; undated (Box 1)
  - Magazines, Nov 1992; Art News (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Biographical notes, author unknown, possibly by Elizabeth Wilson (Box 1)
  - Biographical material by Rhys Caparn (Box 1)
  - Essay, "Art and the Animal" by Rhys Caparn (Box 1)